A Guide to the Daniel J. Kevles papers, Oral History Interview Transcripts FA497
Rockefeller Archive Center
Daniel J. Kevles papers, Oral History Interview Transcripts
1982-1984
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kevles, Daniel J.
FA497
0.57 Cubic Feet 1 document box and 1 half box.
Scope and Contents
Daniel Kevles, a leading historian of science, then at the California Institute of Technology, conducted a series of interviews in the early 1980s as research for his book, "In the Name of Eugenics", first published in 1985. As part of his project, he had interviewed 39 key medical, human, and molecular geneticists from the US and UK. He selected these scientists, based on their involvement from the 1930s to 1950s, with the process to establish human and medical genetics on an epistemologically-sound footing, devoid of the class and race biases and the methodological flaws that had infused the study of human heredity during the heyday of the eugenics movement. The interviewees included Alexander Bearn, Walter Bodmer, Barton Childs, Harry Harris, Patricia Jacobs, Joshua Lederberg, Jerome Lejeune, Victor McKusick, James R. Neel, Paul E. Polani, Laurence Snyder, and Arthur Steinberg.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel J. Kevles is an American historian of science. His work has focused in the areas of the history of eugenics, human genetics, environmetalism, the history of science in society, and the uses of intellectual property, particularly in relation to the life sciences.
From 1964 to 2001 Dr. Kevles served as the chair of the Humanities Department at California Institute of Technology. Since 2001, his professorships include: the Stanley Woodward Professor of History at Yale University and an Adjunct Professor of Journalism at Columbia University.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by last name of the interviewee.
Human genetics; Eugenics -- History
- Human Genetics Interviews, 1982-1984; 1
  - Walter Bodmer, 1982 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    Interview: Imperial Cancer Research Institute, London, England
  - Peggy Brewer-Musgrave and Richard Musgrave, 1984 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Interview: San Francisco, CA
  - John Burn, 1984 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Interview: The Institute for Child Health, London, England
  - Cedric Carter, 1982 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Interview: Clinical Genetics Unit, Institute for Child Health, London, England
  - Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza, 1984 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Interview: By telephone - from Pasadena, CA to Palo Alto, CA
  - Barton Childs, 1982 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Interview: Johns Hopkins University Hospital
  - Cyril Clark, 1982 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Interview: London, England
  - Bernard Davis, 1984 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Interview: Harvard Medical School
  - John Edwards, 1984 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Interview: Department of Biochemistry, Oxford University
  - Charles J. Epstein, 1984 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Interview: University of San Francisco Medical School, San Francisco, CA
  - Charles Ford, 1982 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Interview: Oxford, England (Vicinity)
  - Park Gerald, 1982 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Interview: Boston's Children's Hospital, Boston, MA
  - Harry Harris, 1982 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Interview: University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA
  - Kurt Hirschorn, 1984 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Interview: Mt. Sinai Medical School, New York City
  - Pat Jacobs, 1983 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Interview: By telephone - from Cal Tech to University of Hawaii
  - Hans Kalmus, 1982 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Interview: The Galton Laboratory, University College London, London, England
  - Sylvia Lawler, 1982 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The RAC allows use of this material in accordance with the relevant sections of US copyright law that facilitate fair use by scholars. The RAC explicitly does not own copyright for the content of the interviews and, as such, cannot grant permission to publish any component of this material. The responsibility remains with the researcher to obtain permission from the holders of these rights.
  - Joshua Lederberg, 1984 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Interview: Rockefeller University, New York City
  - Jerome Lejeune, 1982 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Interview: Paris, France
  - O. J. Miller, 1984 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Interview: Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons
  - Aubrey Milunsky, 1984 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Interview: Boston University School of Medicine
  - Ursula Mittwoch, 1982 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - James V. Neel, 1982 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Interview: Ann Arbor, MI
  - Paul Polani, 1982 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Interview: Pediatric Research Unit, Guy's Hospital Medical School, London, England
  - Paul Polani, 1984 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - James Renwick, 1984 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Interview: London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine
  - J. A. Fraser Roberts, 1982 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Interview: Royal Society of London
  - Leon Rosenberg, 1984 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Interview: Yale University Medical School, New Haven, CT
  - Francis H. Ruddle, 1984 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Yale University Medical School. Interview at Parker House, Boston, MA
  - Arthur Salisbury, 1982 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Interview: New York City
  - Ruth Sanger, 1982 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Interview: Medical Research Council, Blood Group Unit, University College London, London, England
  - Harry Shapiro, 1984 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Interview: American Museum of Natural History, New York City
  - Cedric A. B. Smith, 1982 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - John Maynard Smith, 1983 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Interview: Kingston, East Sussex, England
  - Laurence Snyder, 1983 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Interview: By telephone - from Pasadena, CA to Hawaii
  - Arthur Steinberg, 1982 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Interview: Case Western Reserve Medical School, Cleveland, OH